Hey, hey, what's up, my friend? So, in
today's training, you will learn a
momentum trading system that has
generated 535%
over the last 19 years.
You might be wondering, "So, Reiner,
what's the annual return, man?"
Well, let me break it down for you. The
annual return of this trading system is
about 10% a year with a maximum drawdown
of 22%. To put things in perspective,
the S&P 500, if you buy and hold it over
the last 20 years or so,
annual return is about 8 to 10% a year
with a maximum drawdown of 55
percent or even more, depending how far
back you look. So, you can see that this
system has a similar risk profile as a
buy and hold approach, but with much
lower risk. And the best part about this
trading system is that it takes you only
5 minutes a month. So, you have the
freedom to do the things you love. This
can be like your retirement trading
system, and this is as close as a
passive income as you can get because it
only requires 5 minutes per month.
So, if you're interested, then today's
training is for you because I'll walk
you through the concept behind the
system, the exact trading rules, the
entry, the exits, chart examples, and
much more. Sounds good? Then, let's get
started. So, what is momentum trading?
So, momentum trading is a strategy that
goes long on market that have shown
the best momentum, the strongest
momentum. And the way we define momentum
is very simple. It's kind of like
imagine like acceleration, how how fast
did something move over a given time
period. So, for trading, we're looking
at
how many percent increase did the market
did the asset price move over a given
period. Could be over 2 months, 6
months, 12 months, etc.
And the reason why we are looking for
markets that have shown strong momentum
is because
it is likely to continue higher.
So, the concepts behind this strategy is
to identify markets that exhibit strong
momentum. I'll share with you shortly
how we define momentum, and we're going
to hold the position till momen- tum
stalls or show signs of weakness. So,
let's have a look at this trading
system. It's pretty
pretty unique and something that you
might not have, you know, come across
before.
So, this system, we will be trading the
ETFs market, exchange-traded funds, ETFs
market.
And the reason we do this is because I
just want to give you a different flavor
exposure to the different types of
trading systems out there. Can momentum
trading be applied to the stock markets?
Yes. I could go down that direction, but
for this video, I figured, you know,
let's let's do something different. We
will we'll trade ETFs instead. And
again, these ETFs are readily readily
available. You can easily find them
through these different tickers over
here like we are trading gold, the
ticker is GLD. We are trading S&P 500,
the ticker is SPY. Then we have TLT,
which is the Treasury bond, and DBC,
which is the commodities market. The
time frame is monthly. How often do you
come across a trading system that trades
once per month? And the beauty about
this system is you only need 10 minutes
a month, and that's it. And you will
have a system that has consistently beat
the market. So, I'll get to that
shortly. And for risk management, 50% of
your capital for each My bad, this one
shouldn't be stocks, this one should be
ETFs. for each ETF.
And a maximum of two positions. I think
you're probably familiar with what this
means by now because I covered that in
the previous system. If you are
struggling with struggling with what it
means, then just go back and recap.
And because I'm a little bit of OCD, I'm
going to change this right now. For each
ETF, okay.
So, let's have the have a look at the
rules of this trading system.
The rules of the trading system is
really simple, as you can see over here,
just three lines over here.
First one, the ETF is above the 200-day
moving average. Why do we do this? Think
about this. I'll give you 3 seconds. 1 2
3.
The reason is simple. We want to buy or
go long on markets that are in an
uptrend. So, markets that are in an
uptrend, and they have shown the
stronger signs of the strongest
momentum, we want to buy those markets.
But first, we want to make sure that
it's in an uptrend, and we do it by
making sure that it's above the 200-day
moving average. Second one, for the ETFs
above the 200-day moving average,
next thing we're going to do is to rank
them according to their rate of change.
Simply put, right? We want to rank them
based on their price performance over
the last 12 months. So, let's say
let's keep it keep it simple. Let's say
1 2 3 4. Let's say ETF1, ETF2, ETF3,
ETF4. Let's say ETF1 over the last 12
months, it went up 1%. ETF2 went up 2%.
ETF3 went up 10%, and then ETF4, let's
say, dropped 5%.
Now, ask yourself, which among these
four ETFs, which are the
two best-performing ones, assuming that
they are all above the 200-day moving
average?
I'll give you 5 seconds. 1 2 3 4 5.
Okay, the answer is this one and this
one because they has they have the
largest price increase over the last 12
months. And if you're wondering, "How do
I have that shown on the chart, you
know, Reiner? Can you show me which
indicator do I use? What is the rate of
change?" Don't worry, I'll get to that
really shortly. And finally, the last
one is is just go long the top two
strongest ETFs, which is what I've just
explained shortly. I mean, previously.
Okay, now let me walk you through
how
to go about finding, or rather,
identifying this system, right? Using
TradingView charts. So, first thing that
we want to do is to remember we are
trading these four markets, gold, S&P,
bonds, and commodities. So, what you can
do is that if you want to trade this
system, you can create
a new watchlist if you want. Let's see
how do we create a new watchlist. Okay,
over here. I would then, let's say,
create a new list. Let's call this
ETFs.
Okay.
And in ETFs, let's add in the four
tickers that I've shared with you
earlier. GLD is one.
SPY is the other.
The other one is DBC, which is the
commodities, and we have TLT, which is
bonds.
Okay. We have all four ETFs.
So, now, this is done on the I forgot to
mention, on the first trading day of
each month. So, right now, as I'm
shooting this video, it's like the 10th
of July.
So,
you should always do this, or rather,
preferably do this on a fixed trading
day of each month. And for the rules of
this system I shared with you, the
backtest was done on the first trading
day of each month. So, the first trading
Let's assume that, you know, whatever
you're seeing now is the first trading
day of each month. Okay, assume that
this is the first trading day of July.
So, how do you know which ETF to buy
among these four over here? So, if you
remember the rules,
number one, it has to be above the
200-day moving average. So, let's get
out get out the popular moving average
indicator.
I'll change this to 200-
day moving average.
Okay.
There you have it. Okay, so we have
number one, GLD is above it. SPY is
above it.
Commodities is above it.
And bonds is below it. So, we know that
bonds is
out already. So, we we just left three
contenders, gold, S&P 500, and
commodities. So, among these three,
which two should we be buying for this
month? So, this is where we need to
bring out our rate of change indicator.
Just look for ROC or rate of change.
Click on this.
And this one, I'm going to change this
to
12.
Okay? And if you remember, this is a
monthly time frame. We are looking for
over the last 12 months, which is which
ETF has increased the most in price over
the last 12 months. This one, I'm just
going to change this to a monthly time
frame.
And then at this point, I am going to
look at the ROC value, the rate of
change value, which is over here. So,
I'm going to buy the two strongest one
for this month. So, in this case, you I
can see that gold is 34. Again, you can
use Excel spreadsheet or document just
to write somewhere in case you don't
forget.
Gold is 34, okay? You look at S&P 500,
it is 13, as shown over here.
And finally, if you look at DBC, which
is commodities, the value is -1
over here. So, this is a no-brainer,
right? So, this means that for this
month, we need to buy two ETFs, which is
gold and SPY.
And this is the other two ETFs that we
should be buying for this month if you
were to trade this system. And how much
of gold and SPY should you buy? Again,
very simple, we are going with
50% position size and a maximum of
two
positions. So, simply put,
if you let's say you have $10,000,
you will put $5,000 for this month in
gold and $5,000
in the S&P 500 for this month. And that
And that's it, right? This is the
trading system,
the exact trading rules. And this is why
I said that you can
trade this system in less than 10
minutes per month. Now, let's have a
look at the results of this of this
trading system and see how it has fared
since 2016.
Oh yeah, one thing, before I get to the
results,
I also need to talk about the system.
When do you sell the system or when do
you sell the ETFs? So, very simple, you
only sell your ETFs
when it dropped out of the ranking. So,
if it stops being the Let me just go
back to the rules.
If it stopped being the top two
strongest ETF, you sell it and then
replace it with the next strongest one.
And of course, you also sell it if the
ETF goes below the 200-day moving
average, you would sell it as well. But,
let's say for example gold and the S&P
over the last few months it has been
very strong. So, if you trade this
system, you realize that for the past, I
would say, 6 months or so,
there's no trades at all because you're
just consistently holding gold and the
S&P because when you keep rolling, or
rather you keep
scanning
or running the system each month, you
realize the positions is the same.
You're still going to be holding S&P and
gold. Let's say next month come, August,
and you do what I've just shared with
you, realize that S&P and gold is the
ones that you should be holding for the
month as well. But, if you're already
holding it, then there's no reason to
sell. Just continue holding it. And if
that's the case, you'll probably be done
in like what, less than 5 minutes for
the month. Okay? So, this is a monthly
trading system. Don't forget that.
And now, if you look at the rules, or
rather the results, you can see this is
the equity curve of this trading system.
And if if we drill it down deeper, you
can see that since 2006,
in case you're wondering why do we run
this backtest since 2006, it's because
some of these ETFs they are not
available before 2006. So, the earliest
I could start is 2006, which is not bad
because it's before the
2008 financial crisis. So, you have
the chance to, you know,
test this system on multiple crises like
the '08-'09 financial crisis,
Russia-Ukraine war, COVID, etc. And for
this system, 2006 is up 15%, 2024, the
most recent year, up 26%. And we have a
few losing years in between like in 2011
and this one is is it a 2015 and here as
well and here as well. And the losing
years are pretty shallow if you ask me.
It's just single-digit
losses. And later on, I'll share with
you a a trading a trading hack, a
trading tip that I think most retail
traders do not know on how you can
actually reduce the number of losing
years
to just
a handful, right? I'll share with you
that technique later on. So, this is the
results and if you break it down even
deeper, you can see that since 2016,
it's up about 535% annualized basis is
about 10% a year on average.
Winning rate is close to 60%, losing
rate is about 40%. Your payoff ratio is
1.13. So, this means that your average
winners is slightly larger than your
average losses losers. And maximum
drawdown is 22%. Again, we talked about
what is drawdown earlier. So, again, go
back and watch the video if you missed
this part.
And to conclude this trading system, the
pros and cons
for momentum trading and in particular
this ETF trading system, I won't say
this is not a pros and cons
for momentum trading in general because
momentum trading can be applied to
stocks and clearly the pros and cons
will change accordingly. But, for this
system, the ETF one that I just shared
with you, the monthly trading system,
number one is that minimal time
required. 5 to 10 minutes per month it's
all you need to trade this system. And
in fact, I shared with you step-by-step
how to actually execute it earlier.
There's little correlation to the stock
market because even if the stock market
is down, it's bearish,
you could still be making money for the
year. As you've seen earlier, you see
the results earlier. Let's say we have
2008 financial crisis, this system is up
15%.
2020 with COVID, we are up 18%. 2022
with the Russia-Ukraine war, in this
case we're down 3%. So, there's
little correlation to the stock market.
And the reason being is that even if the
stock market
declines or is in a bear market, this
system can go into safe haven assets
like bonds or gold,
which, let's say,
when the overall stock market is
underperforming, other assets,
if they are performing, this system will
switch to those assets that are
performing during those
crisis period, during those recessionary
period. And that's how the system can
still make money even though the stock
market the stock market is bearish.
And the downside to this system, I I
tried to think about it, that but really
the downside could be there's really
nothing much to do to do for traders
want more action, you won't get much
action from this system. And another
thing that I added previously but I
removed is that this system is, I would
say, the returns are kind of like
average. I mean, it's not like
mouth-watering wow, 20-30% a year. It's
about 10% a year
annual returns.
Pretty average if you ask me. But again,
this is is not 10% for all types of
systems under momentum trading because
if you apply momentum trading to the
stock markets, your returns is going to
be higher. So, this is why I didn't put
the returns average over here because I
didn't want you to think that momentum
trading strategy the returns are only
average. So, I removed that portion out.
But, for the ETF this ETF systems,
right? I would say that yeah, this the
returns for this system is
kind of average. But, you have to bear
in mind, right? Even though the returns
is about 10% a year, not super wow, the
maximum drawdown is
pretty low. It's it's only 22%.
So, if you think about it, since 2016,
I believe the S&P 500 have much deeper
drawdown than 22%.
So, again, right? We whenever we look at
returns, we always have to look at it
returns relative to the risk that comes
along with it. Okay? Now, before you go,
I'd like you to get access to this free
training. You can get it at
tradingwithrayner.com/go
or in the description or in the comment
section below this video. So, in this
training, you will discover three
rule-based trading strategies that work
and they're all backed by data. In fact,
the strategy that you've just learned is
actually taken from this training. So,
you will learn,
in other words, two more extra trading
strategies. And again, I'll walk you
through the
trading rules, the entries, the exits,
the risk management, and chart example
so you can quickly understand the
concepts of these strategies. And that's
not all because I would also like to
give you
the PDF slides of this training, the
trading strategies cheat sheets so you
can quickly recap the rules of this
different trading system, and the
backtest report of all these different
trading systems so you can see the
winning rate, the losing rate, what is
the payoff ratio, etc. All the backtest
report given to you in this training for
free. So, everything is free over here.
Just go down to tradingwithrayner.com/go
or I'll put the link somewhere in the
description below or in the comment
section below. Just click on it. You
come to this page and you can get
started immediately. So, with that said,
I wish you good luck, good trading. I
will
talk to you soon.